M SABARISH NAIR

Date of Birth – 28.02.84 Mob: +91-8883337710.

E-mail: nair.contriver@gmail.com

Objective

Seeking a reputed role as Administrator/Human Resource/Logistics/Supply chain/ Purchase/ Warehouse/Transport Professional in a Managerial position, where my 19 years of professional experience in Indian Air Force can be effectively used for the betterment of the organization/company.

Career Overview

An Indian Air Force (IAF) Veteran with 18 years of experience in Administration, Personnel management, Purchase Management, Contracting, Logistics, Transportation, and Inventory management both at subordinate level and at supervisory positions. Highly efficient and diligent administrative professional with excellent skills in delegating responsibilities, supervising and persistent evaluation for effective task/mandate completion. Commitment to uphold organizational policies, procedures and values when working with staff members and motivating them. Further, had an opportunity to prepare Corporate Social Responsibility (CSR) proposals and to liaise with Corporate houses/PSUs for release of CSR funds and ensured its effective utilisation.

Experience

Senior Superintendent (Administration/Secretariat)

(Nov 2019-till date)

(Air Force Wing, Defence Services Staff College, Wellington, Nilgiris)

- Office Administration Creation of Sub-Organizational structure, setting up of new offices, allocation and assignment of duties/roles for the mandate assigned.
- Organise/maintain filing system and database for confidential /important documents.
- Organise online & offline meetings/seminars with internal and external agencies and ensuring smooth/ timely conduct of the same.
- Plan & execute inward/outward movement of personnel to various locations.
- Preparation of Yearly/half yearly budget requirements
- Creation of a pool of vendor/services related contractors such as Building Maintainence (Electrical & Civil), housekeeping staff & other services.
- Allocation of offices/faculty/accommodation, upkeep & maintainence of the same.
- Hiring of passenger vehicles, cargo trucks for official & personal purposes.
- Preparation of Tenders/floating of tenders/ award of contracts/ finalization of Contracts/AMCs and ensuring timely completion of the same by supervision, follow up, analysis and continuous monitoring,
- Monthly/quarterly/half yearly/annual returns preparation of reports/statements on the progress of the assigned mandates/tasks for submission to higher ups.
- Obtain feedback from the faculty members/course attendees with respect to admin related services.

Senior i/c Purchase (Pre-contract and Post-contract) (Aug 2013-Dec 2016) (Foreign Procurement Wing (Air Force Head Quarters, New Delhi)

Key Work Area

- Processing of Purchase Indents (requirements) received from various Stock Holding Depots and Consumer Units.
- Evaluation, Analysis and vetting of Indents.
- Creation of reliable and verified data base for Source of supply (Company/Vendor/Supplier/Manufacturer).
- Preparation of Request for Proposals (RFPs)/ Tender documents with clauses of Warranty, Performance Bank Guarantees, International Commercial terms (INCO terms) etc...
- Floating of tenders manually for registered vendors and digitally for all prospective bidders in public domain
- Conduct of Pre-bid meetings wherever deemed necessary.
- Opening of Tenders/Quotations/Bids by a committee with representative of concerned specialist branch.
- Finalization of prospective vendor and Price Negotiations (PNC) .
- Preparation and placing of Supply order incorporating all terms and conditions of RFP.
- Release of payment by the way of Letters of Credit (LC), Direct Bank Transfers etc after imposing of Liquidated damages (LD) and other charges, if any
- Forwarding of requisite documents viz The Bill of lading, Air Way Bill, RR, LR, Invoices.. to various Consignment and Custom Clearing agents at Air Ports and Ports(JNPT, Kandla Port, IGIA, Kolkata Ports etc.).
- Liaison with transporters for executing prompt and safe delivery of consignments
- Processing of Post contract requisites such as Quantitative and qualitative Discrepancies, Demurrage Charges, Ground rent and allied charges etc...

Provisioning and Indent Executive

(Aug 2009-Aug 2013)

(Stock Holding and Base Repair Depot, Coimbatore)

Key Work Area

- Provisioning components/spares for Five (05) Years Servicing Schedule considering various factors such as consumption pattern, stock holding, lead time shelf life of components/spares, task allotted etc.
- Preparation and compiling list of components/spares based on the user requirements, past consumption patterns and tasks (Number of Aircrafts and components which are allotted for scheduled servicing).
- Segregation data of components/spares based on various source of supplies (SOS) viz Foreign Firm, HAL & other PSUs, Indigenous civil Suppliers, In house manufacturers.
- Preparation, Vetting and Shorlisting of Indents (list of components/spares) SOS wise.
- Placing of Indigenous Supply Orders to vendors and HAL with minimum lead time.
- Forwarding of Indents which Source of Supply is Foreign to Higher Echelons and follow up on the status.

- Prioritizing and procuring the components/spares essential for the current production year.
- Coordinating with the technical production team for optimum utilization of available resources.
- Developed methodologies for effectively monitoring of *Priority Procurement Cases* such as Air craft on Ground (AOGs), Production Held Ups (PHU) ,mandatory spares.
- Played a pivotal role in ensuring extension of ISO: 9001:2008 Certification for the entire Logistics Support Group.
- As part of the Lean-Inventory Concept effectively participated in reducing the production cost.
- Represented the team in various production & progress meetings, instrumental in receiving the best *Supply chain award for 2011-12*.

Stores i/c High Altitude Ration, Specialised Clothing Kits and Rubberized Store (Forward Support Base, Leh Ladakh, J&K) (July 2007-July 2009)

Key Work Area

- Implemented the newly devised policy for Rubberized stores by disposing shelflife expired items and enhanced storage conditions
- Worked upon converting the existing High Altitude Kit Cum rubberized store into a state of the art Warehouse with outmost care for Fire and safety.
- Ensured uninterrupted and precise delivery of *High Altitude Ration* to the troops by judicious placing of requirements to the Suppliers.
- Worked upon fulfilling Consumer requirements in respect of Specialised High Altitude Kits with limited availability of stocks.
- A member of the editorial board for the newly formulated bi-annual station Magazine "THOISE DIARIES"
- One of the team leaders chosen for implementing pastime/hobby activity groups, to overcome High altitude related sickness and to upkeep the morale of troops which ensured they are occupied and are rid of boredom due to restriction in physical activity

Junior Executive:

Transporation, Local/Market Purchase, Stores i/c Aircraft components/spares (Mig-21/25/SU-30-a/c, Chetak/cheetah helicopters), Technical Stores (Radars and electronics) & Vehicles Spares

(Air Force Station, Bareilly, Uttar Pradesh)

(Aug 2002-June 2007)

Key Work Area

- Part of the team leaders chosen for implementing Integrated Material Management On Line System (IMMOLS), an ERP platform.
- Team member for transformation of Logistics from manual system of accounting to digitalization and completed the E-Audit certification from Controller of Defence Accounts.
- Undertook Receipt and dispatch of all sorts of stores such as Aircraft & Radar Components/spares, Electronics, Specialist Vehicle spares, Flying Clothing etc
- Preparation of documents and executing transportation of Goods by means of Air, Road & Post
- Local Purchase of Vehicle Spares & Accessories, high precision Tools,

Lubricants, consumables/durables etc.

- Created Purchase Agreements with authorized dealers of spare/tools supplying Maruti Genuine Spares (MGS/MGA), Tata Spares etc..
- Instrumental in purchasing and supplying kits (Laptops, Tools, Special uniforms etc) for a 250 member Indian Contingent for undertaking joint exercise with France (Exercise Garuda-II) within a short span of time.
- As in charge of stores, was responsible for Book keeping, Storage, Accounting, issue of Components/Spares in Forward Supply System Store attached with Main Hanger lines of Sukhoi-a/c, Mig-21, Mig-25 and Chetak/Cheetah (03 Months at each store).
- Successful dispatch of more than 3200 lines of SU-30 K aircraft spares/equipments/spares (which were on loan/lease from Russia) and receipt of more than 2600 lines of SU-30 MK I aircraft spares/equipments/spares.

Senior Trainee:

(Air Force Station, Tambaram, Chennai)

(Dec 2001-July 2002)

- Training on Logistics, Warehousing, Procurement, Stores, Transportation & Provisioning.
- Undertook Industrial Visits to Ordnance Clothing factories and Air Force Equipment Depots at Avadi.

Junior Trainee:

(Air Force Station, Belagavi, Karnataka)

(Jun 2001-Dec 2001)

Military Training

Education

COURSES	BOARD/UNIVERSITY	YEAR
Diploma in Stores & Transportation	Indian Institute of Material Management	2018
Post Graduation (M.A)	Annamalai University	2010
Graduation (B.A)	Annamalai University	2007
HSC	St.Antony's Boys Higher Secondary School, Nilgiris (Ooty)	2001
SSLC	St.Joseph's Boys High School, Nilgiris (Ooty)	1999

Hobbies – Travelling, Table Tennis, Cooking & Reading.

<u>Languages Known</u>- English, Hindi, Malayalam & Tamil

<u>Preferred Location</u> –Chennai, Bangalore, Mysore, Coimbatore, Calicut, Cochin.

Present Address-

10/229, Jagathala Road Aruvankadu Post Ooty The Nilgiris Tamilnadu-643202

Permanent Address-

Parappurath House Kovilakathumuri Nilambur (Post) Malappuram Kerala-679329